<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd' []>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="std" docName="draft-zatda-dprive-xfr-using-dso-00">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc private=""?>
<?rfc topblock="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="no"?>
<front>
<title abbrev="XFR-using-DSO">DNS Zone Transfer using DNS Stateful Operations</title>

<author initials="H." surname="Zhang" fullname="Han Zhang">
<organization>Salesforce</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street></street>
<city>San Francisco, CA</city>
<code></code>
<country>United States</country>
<region></region>
</postal>
<phone></phone>
<email>hzhang@salesforce.com</email>
<uri></uri>
</address>
</author>
<author initials="P." surname="Aras" fullname="Pallavi Aras">
<organization>Salesforce</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street></street>
<city>Herndon, VA</city>
<code></code>
<country>United States</country>
<region></region>
</postal>
<phone></phone>
<email>paras@salesforce.com</email>
<uri></uri>
</address>
</author>
<author initials="W." surname="Toorop" fullname="Willem Toorop">
<organization>NLnet Labs</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street></street>
<street>Science Park 400</street>
<city>Amsterdam</city>
<code>1098 XH</code>
<country>The Netherlands</country>
<region></region>
</postal>
<phone></phone>
<email>willem@nlnetlabs.nl</email>
<uri></uri>
</address>
</author>
<author initials="S." surname="Dickinson" fullname="Sara Dickinson">
<organization>Sinodun IT</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street></street>
<street>Magdalen Centre</street>
<street>Oxford Science Park</street>
<city>Oxford</city>
<code>OX4 4GA</code>
<country>United Kingdom</country>
<region></region>
</postal>
<phone></phone>
<email>sara@sinodun.com</email>
<uri></uri>
</address>
</author>
<author initials="A." surname="Mankin" fullname="Allison Mankin">
<organization>Salesforce</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street></street>
<city>Herndon, VA</city>
<code></code>
<country>United States</country>
<region></region>
</postal>
<phone></phone>
<email>allison.mankin@gmail.com</email>
<uri></uri>
</address>
</author>
<date year="2019" month="July" day="8"/>

<area>Internet</area>
<workgroup>dprive</workgroup>
<keyword>DNS</keyword>
<keyword>operations</keyword>
<keyword>privacy</keyword>


<abstract>
<t>DNS zone transfers are transmitted in clear text, which gives attackers the
opportunity to collect the content of a zone by eavesdropping on network
connections. This document specifies use of DNS Stateful Operations to enable a
subscribe/publish mechanism for zone transfers reducing the over head introduced
by NOTITY/SOA interactions prior to zone transfer request. This additionally
prevents zone contents collection via passive monitoring of zone transfers
by restricting XFR using DSO to require TLS.
</t>
</abstract>


</front>

<middle>

<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
<t><xref target="I-D.hzpa-dprive-xfr-over-tls"/> enumerates the existing issues with clear text
XFR mechanisms, outlines some use cases for using encrypted channels for zone
transfer and also describes using TLS for zone transfers. It additionally
discusses the various authentication mechanisms that can be used to provide data
and channel authentication, and channel confidentiality.
</t>
<t>This draft describes the use of a DSO <xref target="RFC8490"/> based protocol to perform zone
transfers. This mechanism is heavily based on an existing use of DSO where DNS
clients can subscribe to receive asynchronous notifications of changes to RRSets
of interest: DNS PUSH Notifications <xref target="I-D.ietf-dnssd-push"/>. That specification
was developed with DNS Service Discovery in mind, this document describes an
analogous protocol (XFR-using-DSO) where DNS clients can subscribe to receive
asynchronous notifications of changes to zones of interest, it is developed with
efficient and confidential zone transfers between primaries and secondaries in
mind.
</t>
<t>In the XFR-using-DSO model, a DSO connection is first opened between the
client and server, the client can then subscribe to one more zones to be
notified of changes and the server can push changes to the zone over the
connection. Clients can choose to unSUBSCRIBE-XFR from zone updates at any time.
</t>
<t>Servers can also use the DSO session to send command-style messages to the
client, for example, to instruct a client to stop serving a zone or delete a
zone.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">
<t>The key words &quot;MUST&quot;, &quot;MUST NOT&quot;, &quot;REQUIRED&quot;, &quot;SHALL&quot;, &quot;SHALL NOT&quot;, &quot;SHOULD&quot;,
&quot;SHOULD NOT&quot;, &quot;RECOMMENDED&quot;, &quot;NOT RECOMMENDED&quot;, &quot;MAY&quot;, and &quot;OPTIONAL&quot; in this
document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> and
<xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
</t>
<t>Privacy terminology is as described in Section 3 of <xref target="RFC6973"/>.
</t>
<t>DNS terminology is as described in <xref target="RFC8499"/>.
</t>
<t>DoT: DNS-over-TLS as specified in <xref target="RFC7858"/>
</t>
<t>XuD: XFR-using-DOS mechanisms as specified in this document
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="use-cases-for-xfrusingdso" title="Use Cases for XFR-using-DSO">
<t>This section includes additional use cases in addition to those specified in <xref target="I-D.hzpa-dprive-xfr-over-tls"/> that XuD can offer.
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Security. For some network configurations it is not desirable to have port 53
on the secondary open to an untrusted network for the sole purpose of
receiving NOTIFYs. NOTIFYs can also be trivially spoofed unless secured with
TSIG. For the DSO case, secondaries could initiate DSO connections to the
primary and following that server-initiated DSO NOTIFY messages could be sent
on that connection which could simultaneously be used for SOA and IXFR
requests. This would allow a firewall to be restricted to just allowing
outgoing connections from secondary to primary. Note that a similar but more
constrained mechanism exists for IXFR whereby a short refresh period can be
configured which triggers periodic SOA/IXFR requests from the secondary. TODO:
Look at the details of the NSD implementation.</t>
<t>Performance. For the DSO case, a new subscribe/publish mechanism could be
envisaged that greatly reducing the number of messages required to perform one
transfer.</t>
<t>Improved error handling and retries. In the DSO case new explicit error
codes could be defined that allow a server to indicate the reason for a
failed or aborted XFR request. Also a new client initiated message could be
used to gracefully cancel AXFRs.</t>
<t>New command channel. For the DSO case it would be possible to include new
server-initiated 'control' commands e.g. 'stop serving this zone', 'delete
this zone'.</t>
<t>QUESTION: Is there any case where the primary might want to initiate the DSO
connection to the secondary?</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="overview" title="Overview">
<t>The figure below provides an outline of the XuD protocol.
</t>
<t><eref target="https://docs.google.com/drawings/d/1Jny_OFFXbazhtSAaCMak7nmBzhdzYpywkWz33IkrD7g/edit?usp=sharing">Figure 1: XuD protocol</eref>
</t>
<t>A DNS XuD client subscribes for zone notifications for a particular zone by
connecting to the appropriate authoritative server for that zone, and sending
DSO message(s) indicating the zone(s) of interest. When the client loses
interest in receiving further updates to these zones, it unsubscribes.
</t>
<t>The authoritative server for a DNS zone is any server capable of generating the
correct change notifications for a zone. It may be a primary, secondary, or
stealth name server [RFC7719].
</t>
<t>Standard DNS Queries MAY be sent over a XuD (i.e., DSO) session. For any zone
for which the server is authoritative, it MUST respond authoritatively for
queries on names falling within that zone both for normal DNS queries and for
XuD subscriptions. For names for which the server is acting as a recursive
resolver, e.g. when the server is the local recursive resolver, for any query
for which it supports XuD subscriptions, it MUST also support standard queries.
</t>
<t>XuD imposes less load on the responding server than rapid polling would, but XuD
notifications do still have a cost, so XuD clients MUST only create XuD
subscriptions for zones they are authorised to transfer.
</t>
<t>Generally, as described in the DNS Stateful Operations specification [RFC8490],
a client must not keep a session to a server open indefinitely if it has no
subscriptions (or other operations) active on that session. A client MAY close a
session as soon as it becomes idle, and then if needed in the future, open a new
session when required. Alternatively, a client MAY speculatively keep an idle
session open for some time, subject to the constraint that it MUST NOT keep a
session open that has been idle for more than the session's idle timeout (15
seconds by default) [RFC8490].
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="transport" title="Transport">
<t>XuD clients MUST use DNS Stateful Operations [RFC8490] running over TLS over TCP
[RFC7858].
</t>
<t>The connection for XuD SHOULD be established using port 853, as specified in
<xref target="RFC7858"/>, unless there is mutual agreement between the secondary and primary
to use a port other than port 853 for XuD.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="state-considerations" title="State Considerations">
<t>Each XuD server is capable of handling some finite number of XuD subscriptions.
This number will vary from server to server and is based on physical machine
characteristics, network bandwidth, and operating system resource allocation.
After a client establishes a session to a DNS server, each subscription is
individually accepted or rejected. Servers may employ various techniques to
limit subscriptions to a manageable level. Correspondingly, the client is free
to establish simultaneous sessions to alternate DNS servers that support XuDs
for the zone and distribute subscriptions at the client's discretion. In this
way, both clients and servers can react to resource constraints.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="protocol-operation" title="Protocol Operation">
<t>The XuD protocol is a session-oriented protocol, and makes use of DNS Stateful
Operations (DSO) [RFC8490].
</t>
<t>For details of the DSO message format refer to the DNS Stateful Operations
specification [RFC8490]. Those details are not repeated here.
</t>
<t>XuD clients and servers MUST support DSO. A single server can support DNS
Queries, DNS Updates, and XuD (using DSO) on the same TCP port.
</t>
<t>A XuD exchange begins with the client making a TLS/TCP connection to the
appropriate server.
</t>
<t>A typical XuD client will immediately issue a DSO Keepalive operation to request
a session timeout and/or keepalive interval longer than the the 15-second
default values, but this is not required. A XuD client MAY issue other requests
on the session first, and only issue a DSO Keepalive operation later if it
determines that to be necessary. Sending either a DSO Keepalive operation or a
XuD subscription over the TLS/TCP connection to the server signals the client's
support of DSO and serves to establish a DSO session.
</t>
<t>In accordance with the current set of active subscriptions, the server sends
relevant asynchronous XuD notifications to the client. Note that a client MUST
be prepared to receive (and silently ignore) XuD notifications for subscriptions
it has previously removed, since there is no way to prevent the situation where
a XuD notification is in flight from server to client while the client's
UNSUBSCRIBE-XFR message cancelling that subscription is simultaneously in flight
from client to server.
</t>

<section anchor="xud-subscribexfr" title="XuD SUBSCRIBE-XFR">
<t>After connecting, and requesting a longer idle timeout and/or keepalive
interval if necessary, a XuD client then indicates its desire to receive XuD
notifications for a given zone by sending a SUBSCRIBE-XFR request to the
server. A SUBSCRIBE-XFR request is encoded in a DSO message [RFC8490]. This
specification defines a primary DSO TLV for XuD SUBSCRIBE-XFR Requests
(tentatively DSO Type Code 0x50).
</t>
<t>DSO messages with the SUBSCRIBE-XFR TLV as the Primary TLV are not permitted
in early data.
</t>
<t>The entity that initiates a SUBSCRIBE-XFR request is by definition the
client. A server MUST NOT send a SUBSCRIBE-XFR request over an existing
session from a client. If a server does send a SUBSCRIBE-XFR request over a
DSO session initiated by a client, this is a fatal error and the client
should immediately abort the connection with a TLS close_notify alert. See
Section 6.1 of [RFC8446].
</t>
<t>TODO: Need to define a DSO version of TSIG to cover the SUBSCRIBE-XFR and
DSO-<spanx style="emph">XFR responses, since the Additional section count in DSO message MUST be
zero. Note the client only needs to use TSIG in the SUBSCRIBE-XFR message to
prove it is authorised to request zone transfers, but all DSO-</spanx>XFR messages
should be signed if primary TSIG is required for the authentication model in
use.
</t>

<section anchor="subscribexfr-request" title="SUBSCRIBE-XFR Request">
<t>A SUBSCRIBE-XFR request begins with the standard DSO 12-byte header
[RFC8490], followed by the SUBSCRIBE-XFR primary TLV. A SUBSCRIBE-XFR request
message is illustrated in Figure 2.
</t>
<t>The MESSAGE ID field MUST be set to a unique value, that the client is not
using for any other active operation on this DSO session. For the purposes
here, a MESSAGE ID is in use on this session if the client has used it in a
request for which it has not yet received a response, or if the client has
used it for a subscription which it has not yet cancelled using
UNSUBSCRIBE-XFR. In the SUBSCRIBE-XFR response the server MUST echo back the
MESSAGE ID value unchanged.
</t>
<t>The other header fields MUST be set as described in the DSO spec- ification
[RFC8490]. The DNS OPCODE field contains the OPCODE value for DNS Stateful
Operations (6). The four count fields MUST be zero, and the corresponding
four sections MUST be empty (i.e., absent).
</t>
<t>The DSO-TYPE is SUBSCRIBE-XFR (tentatively 0x50).
</t>
<t>The DSO-LENGTH is the length of the DSO-DATA that follows, which specifies the
name and class of the zone and optionally the SOA value of the client's version
of the zone.
</t>
<t>If the client has no copy of the zone it MUST omit the SOA value to indicate to
the server that a DSO-AXFR is required in response (see the next section).
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center">
                                 1  1  1  1  1  1
   0  1  2  3  4  5  6  7  8  9  0  1  2  3  4  5
 +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+  \
 |                  MESSAGE ID                   |   \
 +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+    |
 |QR| OPCODE(6) |         Z          |   RCODE   |    |
 +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+    |
 |             QDCOUNT (MUST BE ZERO)            |    |
 +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+     &gt; HEADER
 |             ANCOUNT (MUST BE ZERO)            |    |
 +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+    |
 |             NSCOUNT (MUST BE ZERO)            |    |
 +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+    |
 |             ARCOUNT (MUST BE ZERO)            |   /
 +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+  /
 | DSO-TYPE = SUBSCRIBE-XFR (tentatively 0x50)   |
 +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+
 |   DSO-LENGTH (number of octets in DSO-DATA)   |
 +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+  \
 |                                               |   \
 \                     NAME                      \    |
 \                                               \    |
 +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+     &gt; DSO-DATA
 |                     CLASS                     |    |
 +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+    |
 |                     SOA                       |   /
 +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+  /
</artwork></figure>
<t>Figure 2: SUBSCRIBE-XFR Request
</t>
<t>The DSO-DATA for a SUBSCRIBE-XFR request MUST contain exactly one NAME, CLASS
and SOA value. Since SUBSCRIBE-XFR requests are sent over TCP, multiple
SUBSCRIBE-XFR DSO request messages can be concatenated in a single TCP stream
and packed efficiently into TCP segments.
</t>
<t>If accepted, the subscription will stay in effect until the client cancels
the subscription using UNSUBSCRIBE-XFR or until the DSO session between the
client and the server is closed.
</t>
<t>SUBSCRIBE-XFR requests on a given session MUST be unique. A client MUST NOT
send a SUBSCRIBE-XFR message that duplicates the NAME, CLASS and SOA value of
an existing active subscription on that DSO session. For the purpose of this
matching, the established DNS case-insensitivity for US-ASCII letters applies
(e.g., &quot;example.com&quot; and &quot;Example.com&quot; are the same). If a server receives
such a duplicate SUBSCRIBE-XFR message this is an error and the server MUST
immediately terminate the connection with a TLS close_notify alert.
</t>
<t>QUESTION: Is there a use case where a client may want to signal that the version
of the zone it holds has been updated via another mechanism and the zone
transfer should restart from a different SOA than that currently exchanged
between client and server?
</t>
<t>DNS wildcarding is not supported. SUBSCRIBE-XFR requests received for zones
containing wildcards are considered an error (see below).
</t>
<t>A CLASS of 'ANY' (255) is not supported.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="subscribexfr-response" title="SUBSCRIBE-XFR Response">
<t>Each SUBSCRIBE-XFR request generates exactly one SUBSCRIBE-XFR response from the
server. A SUBSCRIBE-XFR request message is illustrated in Figure 3.
</t>
<t>A SUBSCRIBE-XFR response begins with the standard DSO 12-byte header
[RFC8490]. The QR bit in the header is set indicating it is a response. The
header MAY be followed by one or more optional TLVs, such as a Retry Delay
TLV.
</t>
<t>The MESSAGE ID field MUST echo the value given in the Message ID field of the
SUBSCRIBE-XFR request. This is how the client knows which request is being
responded to.
</t>
<t>A SUBSCRIBE-XFR response message MUST NOT include a SUBSCRIBE-XFR TLV. If a
client receives a SUBSCRIBE-XFR response message containing a SUBSCRIBE-XFR
TLV then the response message is processed but the SUBSCRIBE-XFR TLV MUST be
silently ignored.
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center">
                                  1  1  1  1  1  1
    0  1  2  3  4  5  6  7  8  9  0  1  2  3  4  5
  +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+  \
  |                  MESSAGE ID                   |   \
  +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+    |
  |QR| OPCODE(6) |         Z          |   RCODE   |    |
  +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+    |
  |             QDCOUNT (MUST BE ZERO)            |    |
  +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+     &gt; HEADER
  |             ANCOUNT (MUST BE ZERO)            |    |
  +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+    |
  |             NSCOUNT (MUST BE ZERO)            |    |
  +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+    |
  |             ARCOUNT (MUST BE ZERO)            |   /
  +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+  /
</artwork></figure>
<t>Figure 3: SUBSCRIBE-XFR Response Message
</t>
<t>In the SUBSCRIBE-XFR response the RCODE indicates whether or not the
subscription was accepted. Supported RCODEs are as follows:
</t>
<texttable>
<ttcol align="left">Mnemonic</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Value</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Description</ttcol>

<c>NOERROR</c><c>0</c><c>SUBSCRIBE-XFR successful.</c>
<c>FORMERR</c><c>1</c><c>Server failed to process request due to a</c>
<c></c><c></c><c>malformed request.</c>
<c>SERVFAIL</c><c>2</c><c>Server failed to process request due to a</c>
<c></c><c></c><c>problem with the server.</c>
<c>NOTIMP</c><c>4</c><c>Server does not implement DSO.</c>
<c>REFUSED</c><c>5</c><c>Server refuses to process request for policy</c>
<c></c><c></c><c>or security reasons.</c>
<c>NOTAUTH</c><c>9</c><c>Server is not authoritative for the requested</c>
<c></c><c></c><c>name.</c>
<c>DSOTYPENI</c><c>11</c><c>SUBSCRIBE-XFR operation not supported.</c>
</texttable>
<t>Table 1: SUBSCRIBE-XFR Response codes
</t>
<t>This document specifies only these RCODE values for SUBSCRIBE-XFR Responses.
Servers sending SUBSCRIBE-XFR Responses SHOULD use one of these values. Note
that NXDOMAIN is not a valid RCODE in response to a SUBSCRIBE-XFR Request.
However, future circumstances may create situations where other RCODE values
are appropriate in SUBSCRIBE-XFR Responses, so clients MUST be prepared to
accept SUBSCRIBE-XFR Responses with any other RCODE value.
</t>
<t>If the server sends a nonzero RCODE in the SUBSCRIBE-XFR response, that
means:
</t>
<t>
<list style="format %c">
<t>the client is (at least partially) misconfigured,</t>
<t>the server resources are exhausted, or</t>
<t>there is some other unknown failure on the server.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>In any case, the client shouldn't retry the subscription to this server right
away. If a client has other authoritative servers configured for a given zone
an alternative server can be tried immediately.
</t>
<t>If the client has other successful subscriptions to this server, these
subscriptions remain even though additional subscriptions may be refused.
Neither the client nor the server are required to close the connection,
although, either end may choose to do so.
</t>
<t>If the server sends a nonzero RCODE then it SHOULD append a Retry Delay TLV
[RFC8490] to the response specifying a delay before the client attempts this
operation again. Recommended values for the delay for different RCODE values are
given below. These recommended values apply both to the default values a server
should place in the Retry Delay TLV, and the default values a client should
assume if the server provides no Retry Delay TLV.
</t>
<t>For RCODE = 1 (FORMERR) the delay may be any value selected by the implementer.
A value of five minutes is RECOMMENDED, to reduce the risk of high load from
defective clients.
</t>
<t>For RCODE = 2 (SERVFAIL) the delay should be chosen according to the level of
server overload and the anticipated duration of that overload. By default, a
value of one minute is RECOMMENDED. If a more serious server failure occurs, the
delay may be longer in accordance with the specific problem encountered.
</t>
<t>For RCODE = 4 (NOTIMP), which occurs on a server that doesn't implement DNS
Stateful Operations [RFC8490], it is unlikely that the server will begin
supporting DSO in the next few minutes, so the retry delay SHOULD be one hour.
Note that in such a case, a server that doesn't implement DSO is unlikely to
place a Retry Delay TLV in its response, so this recommended value in particular
applies to what a client should assume by default.
</t>
<t>For RCODE = 5 (REFUSED), which occurs on a server that implements XuDs, but is
currently configured to disallow XuDs, the retry delay may be any value selected
by the implementer and/or configured by the operator. Since it is possible that
the misconfiguration may be repaired at any time, the retry delay should not be
set too high. By default, a value of 5 minutes is RECOMMENDED.
</t>
<t>For RCODE = 9 (NOTAUTH), which occurs on a server that implements XuDs, but is
not configured to be authoritative for the requested name, the retry delay may
be any value selected by the implementer and/or configured by the operator.
Since it is possible that the misconfiguration may be repaired at any time, the
retry delay should not be set too high. By default, a value of 5 minutes is
RECOMMENDED.
</t>
<t>For RCODE = 11 (DSOTYPENI), which occurs on a server that implements DSO but
doesn't implement XuD, it is unlikely that the server will begin supporting XuD
in the next few minutes, so the retry delay SHOULD be one hour.
</t>
<t>For other RCODE values, the retry delay should be set by the server as
appropriate for that error condition. By default, a value of 5 minutes is
RECOMMENDED.
</t>
<t>For RCODE = 9 (NOTAUTH), the time delay applies to requests for other names
falling within the same zone. Requests for names falling within other zones are
not subject to the delay. For all other RCODEs the time delay applies to all
subsequent requests to this server.
</t>
<t>After sending an error response the server MAY allow the session to remain open,
or MAY send a Retry Delay Operation TLV instructing the client to close the
session, as described in the DSO specification [RFC8490]. Clients MUST correctly
handle both cases.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="xud-notifications" title="XuD Notifications">
<t>Once a subscription has been successfully established, the server generates
DSO-IXFR messages to send to the client as appropriate. In the case that the
server could not provide a DSO-IXFR message based on the SOA received from the
client an initial DSO-AXFR message will be sent immediately following the
SUBSCRIBE-XFR Response. Subsequent changes to the zone are then communicated to
the client in subsequent DSO-IXFR messages.
</t>
<t>Until an UNSUBSCRIBE-XFR message is received the server MUST assume that the
client is updating the client's version of the zone with the notifications sent
and can therefore hold state on the SOA version the client holds. It MUST use
this to generate the DSO-IXFR messages sent on a XuD session.
</t>

<section anchor="dsoixfr-message" title="DSO-IXFR Message">
<t>A DSO-IXFR unidirectional message begins with the standard DSO 12-byte header
[RFC8490], followed by the DSO-IXFR primary TLV. A DSO-IXFR message is
illustrated in Figure 4.
</t>
<t>In accordance with the definition of DSO unidirectional messages, the MESSAGE ID
field MUST be zero. There is no client response to a DSO-IXFR message.
</t>
<t>The other header fields MUST be set as described in the DSO specification
[RFC8490]. The DNS OPCODE field contains the OPCODE value for DNS Stateful
Operations (6). The four count fields MUST be zero, and the corresponding four
sections MUST be empty (i.e., absent).
</t>
<t>The DSO-TYPE is DSO-IXFR (tentatively 0x51).
</t>
<t>The DSO-LENGTH is the length of the DSO-DATA that follows, which specifies the
changes being communicated.
</t>
<t>The DSO-DATA contains one or more change notifications. A DSO-IXFR Message MUST
contain at least one change notification. If a DSO-IXFR Message is received that
contains no change notifications, this is a fatal error, and the receiver MUST
immediately terminate the connection with a TLS close_notify alert.
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center">
                                 1  1  1  1  1  1
   0  1  2  3  4  5  6  7  8  9  0  1  2  3  4  5
 +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+  \
 |           MESSAGE ID (MUST BE ZERO)           |   \
 +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+    |
 |QR| OPCODE(6) |         Z          |   RCODE   |    |
 +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+    |
 |             QDCOUNT (MUST BE ZERO)            |    |
 +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+     &gt; HEADER
 |             ANCOUNT (MUST BE ZERO)            |    |
 +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+    |
 |             NSCOUNT (MUST BE ZERO)            |    |
 +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+    |
 |             ARCOUNT (MUST BE ZERO)            |   /
 +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+  /
 |      DSO-TYPE = DSO-IXFR (tentatively 0x51)   |
 +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+
 |   DSO-LENGTH (number of octets in DSO-DATA)   |
 +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+  \
 |                                               |   \
 |                                               |    |
 |            IXFR BODY AS PER RFC1995           |     &gt; DSO-DATA
 |                                               |    |
 |                                               |   /
 +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+  /
</artwork></figure>
<t>Figure 4: DSO-IXFR Message
</t>
<t>The DSO-DATA in a DSO-IXFR message is identical to the contents of a <xref target="RFC1995"/>
IXFR message that would be sent to communicate the same zone incremental zone
transfer over UDP or TCP i.e. the set of one or more difference sequences that
follow the DNS Header in an IXFR message.
</t>
<t>When processing the records received in a DSO-IXFR Message, the receiving client
MUST validate that the zone being updated correspond with at least one currently
active subscription on that session. Specifically, the SOA name and CLASS MUST
match the SOA name and CLASS given in a SUBSCRIBE-XFR request, subject to the
usual established DNS case- insensitivity for US-ASCII letters.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="fallback-to-axfr" title="Fallback to AXFR">
<t>The format of the DSO-AXFR message is a standard DSO header with DSO-TYPE of
DSO-AXFR (tentatively DSO Type Code 0x52) and the body is identical to a
<xref target="RFC5936"/> AXFR response body.
</t>
<t>TODO: More detail here.
</t>
<t>If the SUBSCRIBE-XFR message contained no SOA value, the server MUST send a
DSO-AXFR message as its first message on the connection.
</t>
<t>Alternatively if incremental zone transfer is not available, the entire zone MAY
be returned in a DSO-AXFR message.
</t>
<t>QUESTION: Should we bother with a separate DSO-AXFR message or just allow full
zone transfer inside the DSO-IXFR message as with <xref target="RFC1995"/> IXFR? A separate
message type makes is more explicit and IXFR was constrained by having to
respond to a IXFR request.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="xud-unsubscribexfr" title="XuD UNSUBSCRIBE-XFR">
<t>To cancel an individual subscription without closing the entire DSO session, the
client sends an UNSUBSCRIBE-XFR message over the established DSO session to the
server. The UNSUBSCRIBE-XFR message is encoded as a DSO unidirectional message
[RFC8490]. This specification defines a primary unidirectional DSO TLV for XuD
UNSUBSCRIBE-XFR Messages (tentatively DSO Type Code 0x53).
</t>
<t>A server MUST NOT initiate an UNSUBSCRIBE-XFR message. If a server does send an
UNSUBSCRIBE-XFR message over a DSO session initiated by a client, this is a
fatal error and the client should immediately abort the connection with a TLS
close_notify alert.
</t>

<section anchor="unsubscribexfr-message" title="UNSUBSCRIBE-XFR Message">
<t>An UNSUBSCRIBE-XFR unidirectional message begins with the standard DSO 12-byte
header [RFC8490], followed by the UNSUBSCRIBE-XFR primary TLV. An
UNSUBSCRIBE-XFR message is illustrated in Figure 5.
</t>
<t>In accordance with the definition of DSO unidirectional messages, the MESSAGE ID
field MUST be zero. There is no server response to an UNSUBSCRIBE-XFR message.
</t>
<t>The other header fields MUST be set as described in the DSO spec- ification
[RFC8490]. The DNS OPCODE field contains the OPCODE value for DNS Stateful
Operations (6). The four count fields MUST be zero, and the corresponding four
sections MUST be empty (i.e., absent).
</t>
<t>The DSO-TYPE is UNSUBSCRIBE-XFR (tentatively 0x53).
</t>
<t>The DSO-LENGTH field contains the value 2, the length of the 2-octet MESSAGE ID
contained in the DSO-DATA.
</t>
<t>The DSO-DATA contains the value given in the MESSAGE ID field of an active
SUBSCRIBE-XFR request. This is how the server knows which SUBSCRIBE-XFR request
is being cancelled. After receipt of the UNSUBSCRIBE-XFR message, the
SUBSCRIBE-XFR request is no longer active.
</t>
<t>It is allowable for the client to issue an UNSUBSCRIBE-XFR message for a
previous SUBSCRIBE-XFR request for which the client has not yet received a
SUBSCRIBE-XFR response. This is to allow for the case where a client starts and
stops a subscription in less than the round-trip time to the server. The client
is NOT required to wait for the SUBSCRIBE-XFR response before issuing the
UNSUBSCRIBE-XFR message.
</t>
<t>Consequently, it is possible for a server to receive an UNSUBSCRIBE-XFR message
that does not match any currently active subscription. This can occur when a
client sends a SUBSCRIBE-XFR request, which subsequently fails and returns an
error code, but the client sent an UNSUBSCRIBE-XFR message before it became
aware that the SUBSCRIBE-XFR request had failed. Because of this, servers MUST
silently ignore UNSUBSCRIBE-XFR messages that do not match any currently active
subscription.
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center">
                                  1  1  1  1  1  1
    0  1  2  3  4  5  6  7  8  9  0  1  2  3  4  5
  +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+  \
  |           MESSAGE ID (MUST BE ZERO)           |   \
  +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+    |
  |QR| OPCODE(6) |         Z          |   RCODE   |    |
  +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+    |
  |             QDCOUNT (MUST BE ZERO)            |    |
  +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+     &gt; HEADER
  |             ANCOUNT (MUST BE ZERO)            |    |
  +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+    |
  |             NSCOUNT (MUST BE ZERO)            |    |
  +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+    |
  |             ARCOUNT (MUST BE ZERO)            |   /
  +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+  /
  | DSO-TYPE = UNSUBSCRIBE-XFR (tentatively 0x53) |
  +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+
  |                DSO-LENGTH (2)                 |
  +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+  \
  |              SUBSCRIBE-XFR MESSAGE ID             |   &gt; DSO-DATA
  +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+  /
</artwork></figure>
<t>Figure 5: UNSUBSCRIBE-XFR Message
</t>
<t>QUESTION: Do we need the equivalent of a RECONFIRM message from DNS PUSH
Notifcations <xref target="I-D.ietf-dnssd-push"/>?
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="dns-stateful-operations-tlv-context-summary" title="DNS Stateful Operations TLV Context Summary">
<t>This document defines four new DSO TLVs. As suggested in Section 8.2 of the DNS
Stateful Operations specification [RFC8490], the valid contexts of these new TLV
types are summarized below.
</t>
<t>The client TLV contexts are:
</t>
<t>C-P:  Client request message, primary TLV
</t>
<t>C-U:  Client unidirectional message, primary TLV
</t>
<t>C-A:  Client request or unidirectional message, additional TLV
</t>
<t>CRP:  Response back to client, primary TLV
</t>
<t>CRA:  Response back to client, additional TLV
</t>
<texttable>
<ttcol align="left">TLV Type</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">C-P</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">C-U</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">C-A</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">CRP</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">CRA</ttcol>

<c>SUBSCRIBE-XFR</c><c>X</c><c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
<c>DSO-IXFR</c><c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
<c>DSO-AXFR</c><c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
<c>UNSUBSCRIBE-XFR</c><c></c><c>X</c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
</texttable>
<t>Table 2: DSO TLV Client Context Summary
</t>
<t>The server TLV contexts are:
</t>
<t>S-P:  Server request message, primary TLV
</t>
<t>S-U:  Server unidirectional message, primary TLV
</t>
<t>S-A:  Server request or unidirectional message, additional TLV
</t>
<t>SRP:  Response back to server, primary TLV
</t>
<t>SRA:  Response back to server, additional TLV
</t>
<texttable>
<ttcol align="left">TLV Type</ttcol>
<ttcol align="center">S-P</ttcol>
<ttcol align="center">S-U</ttcol>
<ttcol align="center">S-A</ttcol>
<ttcol align="center">SRP</ttcol>
<ttcol align="center">SRA</ttcol>

<c>SUBSCRIBE-XFR</c><c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
<c>DSO-IXFR</c><c></c><c>X</c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
<c>DSO-AXFR</c><c></c><c>X</c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
<c>UNSUBSCRIBE-XFR</c><c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c><c></c>
</texttable>
<t>Table 3: DSO TLV Server Context Summary
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="iana-considerations" title="IANA Considerations">
<t>This document also defines four new DNS Stateful Operation TLV types to be
recorded in the IANA DSO Type Code Registry.
</t>
<texttable>
<ttcol align="center">Name</ttcol>
<ttcol align="center">Value</ttcol>
<ttcol align="center">Early Data</ttcol>
<ttcol align="center">Status</ttcol>
<ttcol align="center">Definition</ttcol>

<c>SUBSCRIBE-XFR</c><c>TBA (0x50)</c><c>NO</c><c>Standards Track</c><c>Section 7.1</c>
<c>DSO-IXFR</c><c>TBA (0x51)</c><c>NA</c><c>Standards Track</c><c>Section 7.1</c>
<c>DSO-AXFR</c><c>TBA (0x51)</c><c>NA</c><c>Standards Track</c><c>Section 7.2</c>
<c>UNSUBSCRIBE-XFR</c><c>TBA (0x52)</c><c>NA</c><c>Standards Track</c><c>Section 7.2</c>
</texttable>
<t>Table 5: IANA DSO TLV Type Code Assignment
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="implementation-considerations" title="Implementation Considerations">
<t>TBD
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="implementation-status" title="Implementation Status">
<t>TBD
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="iana-considerations-1" title="IANA Considerations">
<t>TBD
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security Considerations">
<t>This document specifies a security measure against a DNS risk: the risk that an
attacker collects entire DNS zones through eavesdropping on clear text DNS zone
transfers. It presents a new Security Consideration for DNS. Some questions to
discuss are:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Should DoT in this new case be required to use only TLS 1.3 and
higher to avoid residual exposure?</t>
<t>How should padding be used in IXFR?</t>
<t>Should there be an option to 'pad' an AXFR response (i.e. a set of AXFR
responses on a given connection) to hide the zone size?</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
</section>

<section anchor="changelog" title="Changelog">
<t>draft-zatda-dprive-xfr-using-dso-00
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Initial commit</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

</middle>
<back>
<references title="Normative References">
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.hzpa-dprive-xfr-over-tls.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dnssd-push.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6973.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7858.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8499.xml"?>
</references>
<references title="Informative References">
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1995.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5936.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8490.xml"?>
</references>

</back>
</rfc>
